John Alden Mason Papers 1904-1967 Mss.B.M384
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV. Card Files and Notebooks, 1911-1951; 3 linear feet
  - Notebooks, 1911-1951; 10; 0.5 linear feet
    - Tepecano Trip field notes, 1911-1913; 8 vols.
    - Tepehuan Expedition, Expense Accounts and bank book, 1947-1948; 2 vols.
      Includes accounts (6x3.5")and Durango Bank Book (4x2.5").
    - Various, Tepecan and Nahuatl, 1 vol.;9.5x7"
      "Of small value." ca.25p. containing writing.
- Series V. Class Notes, 1904-1910; 6 boxes
  Notes kept by Mason during his days as an undergraduate and graduate student. Included are several courses each by Edward Sapir and Frank Speck.
  Donated by Anthony F. C. Wallace on behalf of the Dept. of Anthropology, University of Pennsylvania, July 1972.
  - Advanced Anthropology -- Frank G. Speck, Fall 1908; 1 vol.
    Also includes notes on Sapir's course in American Linguistics, 1908.
  - American Ethnology -- Edward Sapir, Spring 1910; 1 vol.
  - American Indian -- Edward Sapir, Second term; 1 vol.
    Taught 2nd term, sophomore year.
  - American Linguistics -- Edward Sapir, fall 1908; 1 vol.
    --Filed with Advanced Anthropology
  - American Linguistics -- Frank G. Speck, 1907; 1 vol.
  - Ethnology, December 1904; 1 vol.
    --Filed with Physical Anthropology
  - European Ethnology -- George Byron Gordon, Spring 1910; 1 vol.
  - General Anthropology -- Frank G. Speck, Fall 1909; 1 vol.
  - Graduate Anthropology, 1904; 1 vol.
  - Indian Linguistics -- Takelma Notes, 1909-1910; 1 vol.
    Includes notes on Takelma by Edward Sapir.
  - Phonetics -- Edward Sapir, Fall 1909; 1 vol.
  - Physical Anthropology, 1 vol.
    Course taught at the University of Pennsylvania during Mason's sophomore year.
  - Prehistoric Archaeology -- Gordon, Fall 1909; 1 vol.
    Also includes notes on Iroquois religion, Mohawk and Seneca, White Cloud and Mr. Williams, 1910.
  - Seminar in Paiute Linguistics and a Text -- Edward Sapir, Spring 1910; 1 vol.
  - Unidentified course, n.d; 1 vol.
- Series VI. Photographs, 1911-1956; ca.1,000 items
  Native American Images note: Over 1,000 black and white silver gelatin photographs, with companion negatives, of the Pima and Tohono O’odham (Papago) tribes of Mexico. Taken by Mason from 1911-1956 during his archaeological and linguistic expeditions to Chihuahua, Durango, Jalisco, Palenque and Sonora, most of the images are ethnological displaying native dwellings, clothing, pottery, dances, cooking, weaving, and fishing customs. Of particular interest are the 1951 archaeological photographs of carvings, skeletal remains, jade masks and other Mayan artifacts of the Temple of the Inscriptions in Palenque. Some Tepecan linguistic notebooks contain ink sketches of phonetic symbols, maps and diagrams of ceremonies. Later photographs, from 1964, are of Peruvian, Honduran and Guatemalan natives. Masons’ interests ranged from archaeology, ethnology, folklore and Native American languages. Note: In the Mexico: Durango folders of photographs is an itemized list with descriptions of 162 prints. Twenty-seven Palenque photographs are housed in the Print Collection, F8.29.16-20; F8.30.1-20; F8.31.1-2.
  - Mexico #1, 1913-1917; ca.100 photos
    - Two Tepecano men, wearing sombreros
    - Tepecano men at market.
    - Jalisco street scene
    - Two Tepecano men with donkey
    - Tepecano men corralling horse
    - Drying skins, mountains of Jalisco
    - Jalisco market
    - Tepecano men planting
    - Tepecano men at shoreline
    - Tepecano men fishing
    - Tepecano woman spinning cotton
    - Tepecano family preparing to cook
    - Sierre Madre Occidental
    - Tepecano couple at shoreline
    - Tepecano thatch-roof dwelling
    - Tepecano family, native attire
    - Rock formation, Jalisco, Mexico
    - Tepecano celebration
    - Tepecano group on mountainside
    - Tepecano man, portrait
    - Tepecano man, portrait, wearing sombrero
    - Tepecano man adding roof
    - Tepecano couple, with head-dress
    - Tepecano group, dwelling
    - Tepecano boy, portrait
    - Tepecano game
    - Tepecanos gathered in public square
    - Tepecano men with masked figure
    - Tepecano man in public square
    - Tepecano woman, chid
    - Three Tepecano men with weapons
    - Tepecano family, outside dwelling
    - Tepecano children near stone wall
    - Tepecano dwelling near hill-side
    - Tepecano child in doorway
    - Tepecano dwellings
    - Tepecano man, dwelling
    - Two Tepecano women, native attire
    - Two Tepecano boys in doorway
    - Tepecano family
    - Tepecano men, group portrait
    - Dirt road, Jalisco, Mexico
    - Three Tepecano men in sombreros
    - Tepecano children carrying stones
    - Jalisco buildings
    - John Alden Mason at Tepecano dwelling doorway
    - Tepecano masked figure
    - Tepecano procession with masked figure
    - Tepecano stick dwelling
    - Tepecano man in doorway
    - Tepecano straw dwelling
    - Tepecano group, public square
    - Tepecano man on hilltop
    - Tepecano men, boys with sombreros
    - Tepecano family holding objects
    - Tepecano woman, infant
    - Tepecano men, celebratory attire
    - Tepecano men, children harvesting
    - Tepecano men, women, at dwelling
    - Tepecano man weaving
    - Tepecano men wading
    - Tepecano men fishing at shoreline
    - Tepecano settlement
    - Three Tepecano men, under rock formation
    - Tepecano stick dwelling, stone wall
    - Tepecano procession with garland
    - Tepecano man squatting
    - Tepecano church
    - Tepecano man, celebratory attire
  - Mexico #2, 1913-1917; ca.150 negatives
    All negatives.
  - Delaware: Slayton Creek Excavation, 1934; 5 photos
  - Mexico: Chihuahua, 1953-1954; 3 photos (Box 3)
    View of Tarahumare Church at Metate, Chihuahua, Dec. 1953; View from the Road between Tonichi and Onavas; Church at Onavas, Sonora, Jan. 54
  - Mexico: Chihuahua (Northern Tepehuan), 1951; 99 photos (Box 3)
    From Babongame, Chihuahua, 1951.
  - Mexico: Durango #1, 1935; 50 photos (Box 3)
    See: "Durango Expedition 1935" (Series III) for identification of photographs by numbers on back. "All duplicates from museum set. Many missing. Set incomplete. 4/26/56. All pictures are numbered and are identified in Durango Expedition."
    - Boat festival, 1935
  - Mexico: Durango #2, 1935; 56 photos (Box 3)
    Continuation of Durango #1.
  - Mexico: Durango #3, 1912, 1948; 6 photos (Box 3)
    Includes:
    a. Southern Tepehuan woman, 1948
    b. Southern Tepehuan man, 1948
    c. Southern Tepehuan man, 1948
    d. Southern Tepehuan informant and wife, 1948
    e. Tepecano village scene, Azquetlan, Jalisco, 1912
    f. Southern Tepehuan man, Pedro, 1948
  - Mexico: Durango (Southern Tepehuan), 1948, 1951; 96 photos (Box 3)
  - Mexico: Jalisco #1, 1913-1917; 16 photos
    Photos of Tepecano villages and people. Includes negatives
  - Mexico: Jalisco #2, 1917; 5 photos
    Photos of Tepecano people; includes negatives
  - Mexico: Jalisco (Weigand), August 1966; 2 photos (Box 3)
    taken by Phil C. Weigand.
  - Mexico: Mayan #1, 1917; 56 photos
    Photos of Uxmal, Chichen Itza, etc. Includes negatives
    - Temple of the inscriptions, 1917
    - Temple of the inscriptions, 1917
    - Mayan stele.
    - Mayan ruins with vegetation.
    - Mayan ruins with wall, windmill
    - Mayan ruins with tower
    - Mayan ruins, stone steps
    - Mayan temple, landscape view
    - Mayan dwelling ruins
    - Mayan temple ruins
    - Mayan wall with glyphs
    - Mayan ruins with columns.
    - Mayan glyphs with stone figure
    - Mayan temple with carvings.
    - Mayan excavation.
    - Mayan temple, pyramid.
    - Mayan wall, pyramid, temple.
    - Mayan temple entrance.
  - Mexico: Mayan #2, 1917; 58 negatives
    Negatives only.
    - Mayan artifacts.
    - Mayan excavation layer
    - Mayan stone figure
    - Two Mayan stone figures
    - Mayan excavation site
    - Mayan temple stela
    - Mayan idol, side view
    - Mayan artifacts, back, side views
    - Mayan temple columns
    - Mayan animal figure head
    - Mayan stone figure, wall
    - Mayan temple excavation
    - Mayan glyphs, stone ruins
    - Mayan ruins, stone head piece
    - Mayan workers
    - Detail of Mayan glyphs
    - Mayan stone fragment
    - Mayan carved borders
    - Mayan stone idol
    - Mayan excavation site trench
    - Mayan ruins, mound
    - Mayan stick formation
    - Mayan carvings at temple
    - Mayan stone blocks with carvings
    - Mayan temple framed in doorway
    - Two Maya men under stone wall
    - Mayan excavation site, stone walk
  - Mexico: Palenque #1, 1951; 26 photos (Box 3)
    Mostly commercial photos of buildings and artifacts at Palenque, including scenes of archaeological excavation.
    - Mask of jade, 1951
    - Tubular-bead jade necklace, 1951
    - Excavation at Palenque, Mexico, 1951
  - Mexico: Palenque #2, 1951; 29 photos (Box 3)
  - Mexico: Sonora #1, 1956; 53 photos (Box 3)
    Images of Pima and other Indians and cliff dwellings taken in Yecora, Maicoba, Onavas, and Tonichi, Sonora.
  - Mexico: Sonora #2, February 1956; 12 photos (Box 3)
    From David M. Brugge: see correspondence with Mason.
  - Miscellaneous, 1953; 1 photo (Box 3)
    Mrs. Robert Drake and family.
  - Papago, 1919; 37 photos (Box 3)
    Includes negatives.
  - Peruvian (largely), Oct.-Nov. 1964; 3 contact sheets (Box 3)
  - Group of men in hats moving material at excavation site in Palenque, Mexico., 1951; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of six men moving an object at an excavation site.
  - Group of men working at an excavation site in Palenque, Mexico., 1951; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of men working at excavation site.
  - Man seated, taking notes at excavation site at Palenque, Mexico., 1951; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of man seated below carved stone, writing in notebook.
  - John Alden Mason and Burt Bascow, full length, profile, informal, seated., 1951; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length, informal view of Maon and Bascow seated and writing.
  - John Alden Mason, full length, standing in cave, Palenque, Mexico., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Mason, standing in cave, near stalactites
- Series VII. Audio Recordings, 1948-1958; 12 tapes
  Audio recordings of native speakers of Northern Tepehuan (3 reels, 1948) and Southern Tepehuan (6 reels, 1948, 1951), the latter recorded at Durango Mexico.
  - Southern Tepehuan language, February 1948; 1 reel, DAT
    Songs and texts recorded by Mason at Durango, Mexico.
  - Southern Tepehuan language, February 1948; 1 reel, DAT
    Song (in Spanish) and texts recorded by Mason at Durango, Mexico.
  - Southern Tepehuan language, February 1948; 1 reel, DAT
  - Northern Tepehuan language, March 1951; 1 reel, DAT
    Speech and songs recorded by Mason at Chihuahua, Mexico.
  - Northern Tepehuan language, March-April 1951; 1 reel, DAT
    Continuation of 12:1.
  - Northern Tepehuan language, March-April 1951; 1 reel, DAT
    Continuation of 12:2.
  - Northern Tepehuan language, March-April 1951; 1 reel, DAT
  - Pima Bajo language, Maicoba dialect, June 1958; 1 reel, DAT
    Recorded on Sonora-Chihuahua border, Mexico. Nacho Lucero Coyote, consultant; Lorenzo Jimenez, interpreter. Recorded by David M. Brugge.
  - Pima Bajo language, June 1956; 1 reel, DAT
    Recorded at Onavas, Yaqui River Valley, Sonora, Mexico. Recorded by David M. Brugge.
  - Yaqui language, 1954; 1 reel, DAT
    Wire recording, spool 1, transferred to tape by Smithsonian Institution.
  - Northern Tepehuan language, 1951; 1 reel, DAT
    Speech, songs, and phonetics, recorded in Chihuahua, Mexico. Wire recording, spools 1 and 2, transferred to tape by Smithsonian Institution.
  - Southern Tepehuan language, 1948; 1 reel, DAT
    Wire recording, spools 3, transferred to tape by Smithsonian Institution.